Mss.506.44.At4
American Philosophical Society
Athénée des arts de Paris letters, 1792-1853
Mss.506.44.At4
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Letters of French scientists, collected for autographic value, on education, natural history, physics, chemistry, and other topics; practically all pertain to lectures at the Athénée; and many are addressed to André-Marie Ampère.
227 items.
Ampère, André-Marie, 1775-1836
Athénée des arts de Paris.
Berthier, Pierre, 1782-1861
Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de, (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850.
Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
Box 1
Biographical/Historical note
Athénée de Paris (1792-1853). The Athénée of Paris was a private school for popular scientific instruction in Paris in the late 18th and first half of the 19th century.
The school was founded by Pilâtre de Rozer in 1781 as the Musée de Monsieurand, and offered adult classes in the sciences. In 1785 it was renamed the Lycée, which seemed a more appropriate name for a teaching institution. After the Revolution, in the Fall of 1792 the school experienced financial difficulties and turned to the French Revolutionary Convention for assistance. It was granted 10,000 livres, but also received criticism from the Jacobins for having “indulged in exaggerated statements and... principles contrary to the public interest.” Its faculty was subsequently purged and the school was renamed the Lycée republicain. Known as the Athenée de Paris after 1803, it continued to serve as an institution for scientific instruction, popular lectures in the sciences, publishing scientific writings and funding for scientific research. The Athénée of Paris has been described as “one of the most underestimated forces in the evolution of French science.” The institution, which endured until 1849, was committed to the two principles: the independence of science and the utility of science. To further these principles, the Athénée functioned as “a self-financing institution,” that raised revenue to support laboratory and library facilities by offering lecture course to fee-paying subscribers. Unfortunately the Athénée was the victim of bad press in its day. After Louis XVIII’s revival of the Académie des Sciences during the Bourbon restoration, the Athénée was gradually perceived as a second rate institution. Nevertheless, the ranks of its instructors included such eminent French scientists as the chemists Antoine Lavoisier, Fourcroy, and Louis-Jacques Thenard; the mathematician Condorcet; and the naturalist and zoologist Georges Cuvier. Many of its faculty also held positions in other academic institutions, but the Athénée offered several unique attractions even for established scientists: first, it was generous in providing laboratories and other demonstration facilities that greatly exceeded state facilities or those available at the École Centrale, and second, it established a reputation for encouraging lecturers to “try out” new ideas and to express their latest thoughts before they received the stamp of approval from the established scientific community.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Sesslers/Sotheby (lot 184), July 2-3, 1962.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection of two hundred and thirty letters includes a variety of correspondence, mostly by French scientists affiliated with the Athénée de Paris, dated between 1792 and 1853. The correspondence contains letters and receipts addressed to lecturers at the Athénée, largely related to curricular matters and remuneration for courses taught, although some express private concerns such as dinner dates and employment opportunities. Much of the correspondence between 1808 and 1836 is addressed to the French physicist and mathematician André-Marie Ampère (1775-1836), Inspector General of the newly formed French university system and, after 1824, chairman of Experimental Physics at the College de France. Many of the letters are addressed the geologist, mineralogist and mining engineer Pierre Berthier (1782-1861) a member of the Academie des Sciences, who discovered bauxite and engaged in research on blast furnaces. The largest number of letters and receipts in the collection [twenty-one items] come from the pen of Henri Marie Ducrotoy Blainville (1777-1850), the zoologist and anatomist trained by Georges Cuvier, who occasionally lectured at the College de France and the Athénée de Paris before becoming a member of the French Academie des Sciences and being appointed to the chair of Natural History. Table of contents available
Early American History Note
This collection is beyond the geographic scope of this guide, but it may be of interest to some early American scholars.
Autographs.; Beyond Early America; Chemistry -- France.; Education -- France.; Natural history -- France.; Physics -- France.; Scientists - France
- Papers
  - Receipt to [Jean Baptiste?] Berthier for 300 livres, Aug. 21, 1792; 4x6-3/4; Domergue, François-Urbain, 1745-1810
    Scope and Contents note
    Paris, A.D.S. 1p.,end. In French.
  - Letter to [Léon] Duforny, Dec. 18, 1792; 9-1/2x7-1/4; Monge, Gaspard, 1746-1818
    Paris, L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Thanks him for publication for the school.
  - Subscription to a school, Nov. 8, 9, 1793; 9x7; Guyton de Morveau, Louis-Bernard, 1737-1816
    Paris, Frimaire 18, 19, An 2 Printed D.filled in in ms.S.: L.B.Guyton, Lagrange, and Dorat-Cubières. 3 items. In French.
  - Letter to [Augustin François] Silvestre, Paris, Nov. 7, 1797; 9-1/2x7; Hassenfratz, J. H. (Jean Henri), 1755-1827
    Brumaire 17 An 6 A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. His ideas on a technical school.
  - Letter to [Augustin François] Silvestre, Paris, Nov. 7, 1799; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Séguin, Armand, 1765-1835
    18 Brumaire an 8(?) A.L.S. 1p.,end.and add. In French. Teaching of chemistry.
  - Letter to [L'Athénée de Paris], Jan. 22, 1800?; 7-1/2x5; Segur, Louis Philippe de, comte, 1753-1830
    Pluvoise 2, [an 8?]. A.L.S. 2p.and add. In French. Will lecture at the school. Concerning his lectures.
  - Letter to [Armand Joseph de] Béthune, Feb. 17, 1800; 8-1/4x6-1/2; Fleurieu, C.P. (Charles Pierre Claret), comte de, 1738-1810
    Paris, Pluviose 28, An 8 A.L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Hopes he can help with the school.
  - Letter to the Lycée Republicain, Feb. 23, 1800; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Le Blond, Auguste-Savinien, 1760-1811
    Paris, 4 Ventose An 8 A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning the telegraph.
  - Letter to Lycée Republicain, Feb. 26, 1800; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Le Blond, Auguste-Savinien, 1760-1811
    7 Ventose An 8 A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Concerning his gift of a telegraph.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Paris, April 18, 1800; 7-3/4x6-1/2; Segur, Louis Philippe de, comte, 1753-1830
    28 Germinal An 8 A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Cannot lecture on a certain date, due to illness, and suggests another date.
  - Letter to [Augustin François] Silvestre, Dec. 2, 1800; 9x7; Fleurieu, C.P. (Charles Pierre Claret), comte de, 1738-1810
    Paris, 11 Frimaire An 9 A.L.S. 3p.,end. In French. Presents publication to the Lycée.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Paris, Dec. 30, 1800; 6-3/4x3-3/4; Ramond, Louis-François, 1755-1827
    9 Nivose An 9. A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Concerning his publication and lecture at the school.
  - Letter to [Charles Pierre] Claret de Fleurieu, December, 1800; 7-1/2x6; Silvestre, Augustin François, baron de, 1762-1851
    Paris, Frimaire an 9 L. 2p. In French. Thanks for publications.
  - Letter to [Lycée Republicain], March 31, 1801; 8x6-1/2; Leroy, Alphonse Louis Vincent Antoine, 1741?-1816
    10 Germinal An 9 A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning his classes in medicine.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Paris, July 5, 1801; 6x4; Perreau, Jean André, 1749-1813
    Paris, 16 Mer. 9 A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his work being placed before the "administrateurs du Lycée".
  - Letter to [Lycée Republicain], July 5, 1801; 8-3/4x6-3/4, 8x6-1/4; Perreau, Jean André, 1749-1813
    Paris, 16 Messidor An 9 A.L.S. 1p.and enc.of 3p. In French. Concerning process of education.
  - Receipt to Monsieur Berthier for 600 francs, June 10, 1802; 4x7; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    Paris 21 Prarial An 11 A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Paris, June 16, 1802; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Hassenfratz, J. H. (Jean Henri), 1755-1827
    Paris, 27 Prairial An 10 A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. His teaching classes.
  - Letter to L' Athénée de Paris, July 10, 1802; 8x6-1/2; Lefevre-Gineau, Louis, 1754-1829
    Paris, 21 Messidor An 10 A.L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Accepts position to teach at the Athenaeum.
  - Letter to [L' Athénée de Paris], Oct. 31, 1802; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Perreau, Jean André, 1749-1813
    Paris, 9 Brumaire An 11 A.L.S. 1p. In French. Presents publications.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Paris, Nov. 20, [1802]; 8-1/2x7; Lefevre-Gineau, Louis, 1754-1829
    29 Brumaire An 11 A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p.and add. In French. Sends address of Dumeril. Wishes to introduce Caussin.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Dec. 17, 1802; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Hassenfratz, J. H. (Jean Henri), 1755-1827
    Paris, Frimaire 16 An 11 A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Cannot teach tonight at the Athenaeum.
  - Letter to L'Athénée de Paris, Dec. 17, 1802?; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Hassenfratz, G. Louis
    [26 Frimaire An 11?,]. A.L.S. 3p.,end. In French. Reports that new machines are necessary for teaching physics.
  - Letter to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, Feb. 18, 1803; 7-1/4x5; Duméril, C. (Constant), 1774-1860
    A.L.S. 1p.,end.and add. In French. Names date for visit from commissioners from l'Athénée.
  - Receipt for 600 livres, Feb. 17, 1804; 4-1/2x8; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    27 Pluvoise An 12. A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Receipt to [Jean Baptiste] Berthier, June 30, 1804; 4-1/4x7; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    11 Messidor An 12. A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Receipt to [Pierre] Berthier, March 29, 1805; 4-1/2x7-1/2; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    Paris, 8 Germinal An 13 A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Receipt to [Pierre] Berthier, Feb. 21, 1806; 4-1/4x6-3/4; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Receipt to [Pierre] Berthier, July 22, 1806; 4-1/2x7; Biot, Jean Baptiste, 1774-1862
    Paris, A.D.S. 1p. In French.
  - Letter to [G. A.] Bordier[-Marcet], Paris, March 17, 1807; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Girard freres
    L. 3p.and add.with mathematical notes on address leaf; In French. Concerning the lamps invented by Argand and Bordier.
  - Letter to [William] Hamper, Paris, July 31, 1808; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Milcent, Cit. (Jean Baptiste Gabriel Marie de), 1747-1833
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Wishes to meet and talk with him.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampére, Aug. 23, 1808; 7x4-1/2; Wailly, E.A. de (Etienne Augustin de), 1770-1821
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Education matters.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampère, Paris, Jan. 18, 1809; 8x6-1/2; Mermet, Louis François Emmanuel, 1763-1825
    Concerning possible opening in the new University.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Paris, Feb. 16, 1809; 7x4-1/2; Desmarets
    A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning a machine to measure fragility of porcelain.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Aug. 9, 1809; 10x8; Institut de France. Classe des sciences mathématiques et physiques
    Paris, L.S.: G. Cuvier. 1p.and add. In French. Admits him to the class of naturalists.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Paris, Sept. 21, 1809; 7-1/2x5; Petitot, M. (Claude Bernard), 1772-1825
    Paris, L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Notifies him commission has met.
  - Letter to "Les Administrateurs de l'Athénée de Paris, March 22, 1810; 9-1/4x7; Thénard, Louis Jacques, baron, 1777-1857
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. in French. Resigns due to public embarrassment when refused admittance to a lecture.
  - Letter to ----, July 16, 1811; 9x7-1/2; Izarn, Joseph, 1766-1847
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Forwards publications. Flattering letter.
  - Letter to [André Ampère?], Oct. 29, 1811; 7-3/4x5; Dinet
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Has a friend who wishes to talk with him and suggests an hour.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Paris, Nov. 27, 1811; 8x4-3/4; Roman
    A.L.S. 1 p. and add., end. In French. Introduces Sanchez and describes his invention.
  - Letter to the Secretary of l'Athénée royal, Dec. 22, [1811]; 8-1/4x6-1/2; Pillet, Fabien, 1772-1855
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his appearances on the program.
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, June 6, 1813; 7-3/4x4-3/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    A.D.S. 1p., end. In French.
  - Letter to [Léon] Duforny, Paris, July 14, 1813; 7-3/4x4-3/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Complains on delay in beginning meetings.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Aug. 13, 1814; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Fontanes, Louis, marquis de, 1757-1821
    Paris, Printed L.filled in in ms.S. 1p. In French. Announces the honor of "la décoration du Lys" from the king to him.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Sept. 13, 1814; Dejean, Pierre François Marie Auguste, comte, 1780-1845
  - Letter to Monsieur Voisel, Nov. 26, 1814; 9-1/2x8; Pillet, Fabien, 1772-1855
    A.L.S. 1p. Remarks of the Journal de Paris on papers at l'Athénée de Paris.
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Paris, Nov. 28, [1814]; 6-1/4x4; Maurice, F. G. (Frédéric Guillaume), 1750-1826
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. In French. Congratulates hilm. Concerning him as a mathematician.
  - Letter to the secretary of the Athénée de Paris, Sept. 26, [1815]; 7-3/4x5; Pillet, Fabien, 1772-1855
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Wants an account of what transpired at l'Athénée during 1814.
  - Letter to [André] Ampére, Paris, 1815-1816; 8-1/2x6-3/4; Mermet, Louis François Emmanuel, 1763-1825
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Incomplete(?). Will help him. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [André Ampère?], Jan. 12, 1816; 9-1/2x7; Séguin, Armand, 1765-1835
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Asks for his help in applying for membership in an organization.
  - Letter to ----, July 27, 1816; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Aillaud, Pierre Toussaint, 1759-1826
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Concerning his publication on the evils of revolutions.
  - Letter to the secretary of l'Athénée de Paris, Nov. 5, 1816; 6x4; Mollevaut, C. L. (Charles Louis), 1776-1844
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Is busy and may not attend meetings.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampére, Paris, Nov. 27, 1816; 8x6-1/4; Pommier
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p. and add. In French. Asks favor of the school.
  - Letter to Monsieur Woisel, Paris, Dec. 6, 1817; 7-3/4x5; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his meeting next Wednesday.
  - Letter to ----, Feb. 24, 1818; 8x6-1/4; Jacotot, Pierre, 1755-1821
    Dijon, L. 1p. Copie. In French. Requests additional favors for Jean Joseph Jacotot and himself.
  - Receipt for 500 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, March 9, 1818; 4-1/4x6-1/2; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Letter to l'Athénée de Paris, May 7, 1818; 9x7-1/4; Pariset, Etienne, 1770-1847
    Bicétre, A.L.S. 1p. In French. Concerning publication of the seances.
  - Letter to [André Ampère?], Oct. 21, 1818; 7-3/4x5; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p., end. In French. Sends note to be added to the program.
  - Letter to Monsieur Béné, Paris, Nov. 5, 1818; 9x7-1/4; Ragon, Jean Marie, 1781-1862
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. In French. His ideas on teaching history.
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, July 11, 1819; 4-1/4x6-1/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, March 22, 1820; 4-1/4x6-1/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Letter to Monsieur Wirkelle, Paris, April 28, 1820; 10-1/4x8; Robiquet, Pierre-Jean, 1780-1840
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his chemistry lectures.
  - Receipt for 600 francs for payment for teaching, June 5, 1820; 4-1/4x6-1/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Letter to [André] Ampère, Aug. 11, 1820; 7-1/4x4-3/4; Stapfer, Philippe Albert, 1766-1840
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Hopes to visit with him shortly, but a migraine headache prevents his visiting now.
  - Letter to Monsieur Woiselle, Paris, Dec. 6, 1820; 6-1/2x4-1/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning tickets for a lecture.
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, June 20, 1821; 5x8; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, June 21, 1821; 4x7; Robiquet, Pierre-Jean, 1780-1840
  - Letter to l'Athénée de Paris, Oct. 25, 1821; 9-1//4x7; Virey, J.J. (Julien-Joseph), 1776-1847
    Paris, L.S. 1p. In French. Has received his publication and praises them for their kindness.
  - Letter to l'Athénée de Paris, Oct. 31, 1821; 8x5; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Will teach.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 8, 1821; 8-1/4x6-1/4; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 3p. In French. Makes a change on the program. Concerning his lectures.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 15, 1821; 8x6; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning a new publication. Refers to Viollet le Duc.
  - Letter to ----, Nov.17, 1821; 8x6; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. Concerning the introduction to his work and his courses which he will teach.
  - Letter to ----, Dec. 13, 1821; 8x6; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 2p.and end. In French. Changes in his lecture schedule.
  - Letter to ----, Feb. 13, 1822; 7-1/2x5; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Cannot lecture tonight.
  - Receipt to the Athénée de Paris for 600 frances, April 11, 1822; 5-1/4x8; Robiquet, Pierre-Jean, 1780-1840
  - Letter to ----, June 6, 1822; 8x6; Lingay, J. (Joseph), d. 1851
    A.L.S. 2p. In French. Cannot lecture today and lists subjects for future lectures.
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris for 600 francs, June 12, 1822; 4-1/4x6-1/2; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Receipt to l'Athènèe de Paris for 500 francs, June 29, 1822; 4x7; Prévost, Constant, 1787-1856
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampére, Paris, July 31, 1822; 9x7; Izarn, Joseph, 1766-1847
    Stockholm, A.L. 2p. and add.,end. In French. Concerning education in Sweden.
  - Letter to Monsieur Woiselle, Aug. 30, 1822; 7-1/4 x 4-3/4; Bodin, Félix, 1795-1837
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. In French. Goes to England and suggests people who might lecture.
  - Letter to l'Athénée de Paris, Sept.(?) 23, 1822; 9-1/2x7; Robiquet, Pierre-Jean, 1780-1840
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Asks when he will begin his lessons.
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris, April 11, 1823; 4-1/4x6-3/4; Robiquet, Pierre-Jean, 1780-1840
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampère, Paris, June 1, 1823; 9-1/2x7-1/4; Dutrochet, Henri, 1776-1847
    L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning a memoire on physics.
  - Petition to the Grand-Maitre de l'Université de France, Oct. 1, 1823; 12x8-1/4; Socquet, Joseph Marie, 1771-1839
    Lyon, D.S. 2p.,end. In French. Requests permission to teach physics and chemistry in Lyon.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 16, 1823; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Séguin, Armand, 1765-1835
    A.L.S. 1p. In French. "Je vous prie d'agréer l'honneur de cet ecrit."
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Jan. 26, 1825; 8x5; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Dates for other lessons.
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris for 400 francs, April 6, 1825; 5x8; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
  - Letter to ----, April 19, 1825; 8x5; Becquerel, Alexandre Edmond, 1820-1891
    A.L.S. 2p. In French. Forwards publication.
  - Letter to ----, May 2, 1825; 8x5; Virey, J.J. (Julien-Joseph), 1776-1847
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning his acceptance of the post of professor of natural history.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampère, June 13, 1825; 9-3/4x7-1/2; Duhamel, M. (Jean Marie Constant), 1797-1872
    A.L.S. 1p.,end.and add. In French. Concerning a publication of his.
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris for 600 francs, July 11, 1825; 4-1/2x6-1/2; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris for 400 francs, July 14, 1825; 4-1/2x7-1/4; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
  - Receipt to l'Athénée de Paris for 600 francs, Aug. 6, 1825; 5x7-1/2; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampère, Paris, Aug. 31, 1825; 8x5; Bulletin universel des sciences et de l'industrie
    Paris, A.L.S.: Saigey. 1p.and add. In French. Forwards publication by Nobili.
  - Letter to ----, Oct. 19, 1825; 10x7-3/4; Prévost, Constant, 1787-1856
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning a course in geology he wishes to give at l'Athénée de Paris.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Paris, Jan. 19, 1826; 9-3/4x7-1/4; Demonferrand, Jean Baptiste Firmin, 1793-1844
    Versailles, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his lectures on electricity.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, March 8, 1826?; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. His next lecture at l'Athénée.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampére, Paris, April 20, 1826; 9x7; Robinet, Stéphane, 1799-1869
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add. In French. Chemistry problem and his teaching of chemistry.
  - Letter to ----, June 10, 1826; 12-1/4x8-3/4; Société d'agriculture, sciences et industrie de Lyon
    Lyon, A.L.S.: Trolliet. 4p. In French. Reports on findings of the society.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Paris, July 3, 1826; 7-1/2x6-1/4; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Asks to have the rest of his pay forwarded to the south of France.
  - Letter to Monsieur Courbarim, Paris, Sept. 24, 1826; 8-1/2x6-1/2; Dunoyer, Charles, 1786-1862
    A.L.S. 1p.,end.and add. In French. Cannot continue to lecture under the conditions proposed by l'Athénée.
  - Letter to ----, Sept. 29, 1826; 7-1/4x4-3/4; Laugier, M., 1770-1832
    A.L.S. 1p.,end. In French. Concerning tickets for the museum.
  - Letter to A[u]g[us]te Courbarim, Paris, Nov. 30, [1826]; 8-1/4x5; Maisonabe(?)
    A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Will talk on orthopedic deformities in humans.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Dec. 18, 1826; 6x4; Jussieu, Adrien de, 1798-1853
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. In French. Concerning lectures on geology by Constand prevost to be presented at l'Athénée de Paris.
  - Receipt for 600 francs from l'Athénée de Paris, April 11, 1827; 4-1/4x6-1/2; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Paris, July 2, 1827; 9-1/2x7-1/4; Dupin, Charles, baron, 1784-1873
    Paris, L.S. 1p. In French. Will lecture free of charge.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Paris, Nov. 14, 1827; 8x6-1/4; Blainville, H.-M. Ducrotay de (Henri-Marie Ducrotay), 1777-1850
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and add. In French. Concerning his course at l'Athénée de Paris.
  - Letter to [Léonard Peuch?] Dupont, Paris, Feb. 18, 1828; 7-3/4x5; Prévost, Constant, 1787-1856
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p.and add. In French. Concerning this lectures on geology to be given at l'Athénée de Paris.
  - Letter to [André Marie] Ampère, April 23, 1828; 10x7-3/4; Pouillet, M. (Claude Servais Mathias), 1791-1868
    A.L.S. 2p.and add. In French. Concerning courses in physics.
  - Letter to ----, June 22, 1828; 10x8; Vincent, Alexandre Joseph Hidulphe, 1797-1868
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. In French. Concerning mathematics.
  - Letter to [Marie Alexandre] Lenoir, Paris, Nov. 8, 1828; 8-3/4x7; Babinet, M. (Jacques), 1794-1872; Demonferrand, Jean Baptiste Firmin, 1793-1844